<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations on Mr. Harrington's Common-wealth of Oceana: restrained to the first part of the preliminaries.</title>
            <author>Wren, M. (Matthew), 1629-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3676B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1659_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863836</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863836</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96967)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 208:E1659[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations on Mr. Harrington's Common-wealth of Oceana: restrained to the first part of the preliminaries.</title>
                  <author>Wren, M. (Matthew), 1629-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 94, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand at the Golden ball in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Matthew Wren.</note>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harrington, James, 1611-1677. --  Commonwealth of Oceana --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Republics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116051:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> CONSIDERATIONS ON M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Harrington</hi>'s COMMON-WEALTH OF OCEANA: Reſtrained to the firſt part of the Preliminaries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> at the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ball in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116051:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:116051:2"/>
            <head>A Letter ſent to Dr. <hi>W.</hi> W. of <hi>W.</hi> C. By whom the Author was deſired to give his judgement concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Commonwealth of <hi>OCEANA.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am to give you thanks for the occaſion you have given me of reading the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Oceana;</hi> which Book I finde to be ſo much the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of good companies, that not to have ſeen it would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a man to ſome ſhame: But to deale freely with you, I
<pb facs="tcp:116051:3"/> have cauſe to complain of your ſeverity in impoſing a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity upon me to give you my thoughts about it; for in a matter of ſo obſcure and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſpeculation as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Government, it will be difficult not to loſe the way, eſpecially for one very little acquainted in the Reſorts of Learning and Experience. Yet to ſhew you Sir, that my own convenience is not allowed to be an Exception againſt any of your commands, with this you ſhall receive ſome Papers, and in them an account of ſuch things wherein either M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringtons</hi> want of demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or my own want of capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb facs="tcp:116051:3"/> have not ſuffered me to receive ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe men Sir, who have the good fortune to have part in your friendſhip, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e not more in love with any of your vertues, then with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous freedome you maintain in an Age overrun with paſſion and ſoureneſs: It is not enough with you, for the ruining a man, to be told that he is of ſuch a party or perſwaſion, but Truth and Merit are never ſtrangers to your good opinion, in what Country ſoever they have been brought up: This is the Prerogative of your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which being able to paſs ſentence upon every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb facs="tcp:116051:4"/> is not put to take things in groſſe upon the credit of any faction or company of men. The knowledge of this fair temper gives me aſſurance that though I had in charge from you to put down what I could object to Mr. <hi>Harrington's Oceana,</hi> the liberty will not be unaceptable that I take in telling you, There are in it many things deſerving praiſe, a ſprightly expreſſion, and a ſort of Oratory wel becomming a Gentleman, good remarques out of ancient and modern Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and a judgement not ill founded on paſt &amp; preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, were it not for a certain violence in ſeeking to draw all
<pb facs="tcp:116051:4"/> things into ſervitude to his Hypotheſis.</p>
                  <p>Having thus let you know that I do not mean to fall out with the whole Book, it is fit that next I inform you what part of it I reſolve to attacque; And in that my choice ſhall be directed by the imitation of good Greyhounds who if let ſlip at the whole Herd, will, run at none but the Leading Deer: The firſt part of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liminaries is that I faſten on, which is the Groundwork of the whole Diſcourſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the debate of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal and rational notions of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, aſſerted by examples of the Greek and Roman Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory will very properly become
<pb facs="tcp:116051:5"/> the ſubject of a Diſquiſition. As for the following model of a Commonwealth, Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> hath by tranſcribing her Orders very wiſely put himſelf under the Protection of the moſt ſerene Republique of <hi>Venice,</hi> againſt whom I have no inclination to make War, at this time eſpecially when do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo would look like an Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation with the <hi>Turk,</hi> the common enemy of Chriſtendom.</p>
                  <p>In making out this Deſign I have not been able to find out any more proper Method then to follow Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> foot by foot, ſetting down the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in him to which every thing refers, though I am ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how diſadvantageous this
<pb facs="tcp:116051:5"/> is by cutting off all Ellegancy and freeneſſe of Expreſſion, which is no more to be expected from one who ties himſelf to ſuch a Method, then an high Dance from a Man in Fetters: Beſides, whereas to read it over throughly for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it, is more then a Book can often obtain of the Reader; This Piece will lie a great deale more at his mercy, ſeeing that to make ſenſe of it, it will be requiſite to read ſo much of Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> as it pretends to anſwer.</p>
                  <p>But I beſeech you Sir, are not We the writers of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques ſomewhat a ridiculous ſort of People? Is it not a fine piece of folly for private men
<pb facs="tcp:116051:6"/> ſitting in their Cabinets to rack their brains about models of government? Certainly our Labours make a very pleaſant Recreation for thoſe great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages who ſitting at the Helm of Affairs have by their large Experience not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the perfect art of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but have attained alſo to the Comprehenſion of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Foundation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: To them I believe We ſhall appear juſt as Wiſe as the Philoſopher who read a Lecture of the Duty of a good Commander before the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Captain of his Age.</p>
                  <p>To be exempted from this Cenſure will be a very great kindneſſe which is in your
<pb facs="tcp:116051:6"/> Power to doe me by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Papers in ſome cloſe place from whence they can make no Eſcape; They are I confeſſe ſo abſolutely made yours that there remains with me no Power over them, but onely to beg of you that your favour to them may not prove want of juſtice to me.</p>
                  <p>I am not ignorant Sir with what artifice and importunity Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath courted oppoſition from others. And you have told me, that he hath profeſſed himſelf not capable of any greater kindneſs or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, then to have objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt what he had publiſhed. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I ſhould think it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb facs="tcp:116051:7"/> or unreaſonable to expect, that theſe Animadverſions ſhould not be any offence or provocation to him; And yet I am not without ſome reaſon to ſuſpect the contrary: ſince I have ſeen by his rigor to Dr. <hi>Ferne,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> is of a nature that does not willingly admit of Oppoſition. In earneſt ſir, to ſpeak frankly, his uſage of the Doctor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me very harſh, and I can make no better of it then if he ſhould preſs a Gentleman ſo far as to whiſper a modeſt Challenge into his Ear, and then with the help of his Foot-boy make a ſtreet-Debate of that which ought to be decided in the way of Honour. Yet I
<pb facs="tcp:116051:7"/> ſhall be very little liable to this Danger, both becauſe it is likely he will think me below his Revenge, and becauſe not knowing me he will be at a loſs how to aim his blows in the Dark.</p>
                  <p>If then theſe Papers happen at any time to be ſo diſpoſed of by you that they come to give Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of looking on them, I deſire he may only know they were wrote by a Perſon who though he agrees not with his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath a great reſpect for his good parts, And that he is one who neither is nor ever hopes to be within the reach of his <hi>Agrarian:</hi> If you pleaſe he may be aſſured alſo that I am
<pb facs="tcp:116051:8"/> none of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, which he complains hath been about his Ears, not having the leaſt intereſtin a Gown. But perhaps this laſt declaration was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſince it may be hoped that Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> does not yet think ſo meanly of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie as to believe ſo ſlight a Piece could proceed from any Member of it.</p>
                  <p>However I may miſtake in my Apprehenſions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I give it you upon my word Sir, I know very well what belongs to Obedience, as you ſhall receive Teſtimonie whenſoever you pleaſe to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with any more of your commands</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The humbleſt of Your faithful Servants.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116051:8"/>
            <head>Conſiderations on the Commonwealth of OCEANA.</head>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAnotti</hi> divideth the whole ſeries of Government into two Periods, The one ending with the liberty of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the Courſe of Ancient Prudence, followed by the Greeks and Romans; The other being the Courſe of modern Prudence, was introduced by the Huns, Goths and Vandals, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Jannoti</hi>'s Diviſion of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (of which the Author of <hi>Oceana</hi> is ſo well perſwaded that he builds up his Definitions of Government, and the frame of his whole Diſcourſe upon it) may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116051:9"/> ſafely be admitted if he means only that the Greeks and Romans were before the Goths and Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, or that <hi>Solon</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi> were dead long before <hi>Theodoricus</hi> or <hi>Genſeric</hi> were born; But if his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention be (as Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> ſeems to underſtand him) that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the time of <hi>Antient Prudence</hi> the Greeks and Romans obſerved a way of Government free from thoſe imputations of paſſion and violence with which the government of ſucceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (and that generally proves to be Monarchicall) is chargeable, it will be neceſſary to propoſe ſome Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſeems to be a defect of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to think that the Greek and Roman actions are only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in Antiquity; It is very frequent with ſuch as have been converſant with Greek and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Authors to be led by them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116051:9"/> into a belief that the reſt of the World were a rude inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people, &amp;c. which is a term they very much delight in, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether barbarous. This humour was even among them a mean &amp; ſervile addiction to narrow Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and a piece of very Pedanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call pride; but in us who have not the ſame temptation of intereſt, it would be downright folly. In this queſtion the Examples of <hi>the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> (not to inſiſt upon the new diſcoveries of the <hi>Chineſe</hi> Hiſtory) cannot without groſs partiality be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; and their government will not onely be found to have been Monarchical, but alſo in a more abſolute and arbitrary form (if I miſtake not very much) then is to be met with at preſent in any kingdom of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But then, they who have not yet paſſed their Novitiat in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116051:10"/> are not ignorant that origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally all Government among the Greeks was Regal; At the War of <hi>Troy</hi> we find them commanded by their Kings &amp; Princes, &amp; <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1</note> ſays expreſly that it was not till after the taking of <hi>Troy,</hi> which filled Greece with arrogance and riches, that hereditary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies degenerated into tyrannies. And then it was that the Grecians out of an extreme a verſion to that which was the cauſe of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſufferings, ſlipt into Popular Government; not that upon calm and mature Debates they found it beſt, but that they might put themſelves at the greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (which ſpirit uſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies all Reformations) from that with which they were grown into diſlike. Yet <hi>Macedon</hi> an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant part of <hi>Greece,</hi> and that which lifted the Grecian name to the higheſt pitch of glory, never
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116051:10"/> ſuffered this change, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued under a ſucceſſive Royalty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The foundation of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſtate was in Kingſhip; and if it be conſidered how accidental, tumultuary, and violent the change was, there will be very little from thence to be inferred to the credit of the ſucceeding go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>After theſe Conſiderations I muſt profeſs I am not convinced of any utility in this Diviſion of ancient and modern prudence, or that a Court of Claims would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the pretentions to ancient prudence, which are laid by that kind of government which <hi>Oceana</hi> endeavours to aſſert.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</hi> Relation being had unto theſe two times, Government (to define it according to ancient Prudence) is an Act inſtituting and preſerving a Civil ſociety of men upon the foundation of common Right or Intereſt; or it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116051:11"/> the Empire of Laws and not of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Government (according unto Modern Prudence) is an Act whereby ſome man or few men ſubject a City or a Nation, and rule it according to his or their private Intereſt, which may be ſaid to be the Empire of men and not of Laws.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>If then this Diviſion of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have loſt it's credit, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions of the ſeveral Members of it need not be conſidered fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that they come not at all up to the firſt and remoteſt Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of government, in the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and origination of it, about which is all the difficulty; and being here neglected, there is little reaſon to hope the ſubſequent Diſcourſe can have in it the Light of probable ſatisfaction, much leſs the force of infallible Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> The former kind is that which Machiavell hath gone about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116051:11"/> and Leviathan goes about to deſtroy, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I do not think my ſelf bound to undertake all Challenges that are ſent to Mr. <hi>Hobs:</hi> but the eaſineſſe of the Defence in this Particular that Men Govern and not Laws, tempts me to be his ſecond. To ſay that Laws doe or can Govern, is to amuſe our ſelves with a form of ſpeech, as when we ſay Time or Age or Death does ſuch a thing; To which indeed the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Poets or Superſtition of Women may adapt a Perſon, and give a Power of Action; but Wiſe men know they are only expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch Accidents and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications as belong to things and Perſons. He that requires Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from another, cannot ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally do ſo unleſſe he declare what thoſe things are, both to be done and not to be done, in which this obedience is to be paid; This
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116051:12"/> Declaration of the Will of the ſoveraign Power is called Law, which if it outlives the perſon whoſe Will it was, it is only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the perſons who ſucceed in power are preſumed to have the ſame Will, unleſs they manifeſt the contrary, and that is the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of a Law: So that ſtill the Government is not in the Law, but in the perſon whoſe Will gives a being to that law. This declared Will of thoſe who have power is of the Eſſence of law; the puniſhment expreſt, I conceive is not ſo; For it is enough for me to obey the Will of a perſon, that I know hath power to hurt me, though I do not know particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what the hurt is he will doe me; and therefore as ſome laws are, ſo all might have been with leaving the puniſhment at the diſcretion of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>In the ſimilitude, the great Gun
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116051:12"/> is not well traverſed to this point. If the Proportion of things be accurately conſidered, it will appear that the laden Canon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers not to the laws but to the power of the perſon whoſe Will creates thoſe laws, without which power he might be as as ſafely diſobeyed, as that Gunner may be contemn'd who hath neither powder nor Bullet in his Piece.</p>
            <p>The whole force of the next Objection againſt Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts but to this; That becauſe <hi>Hervey</hi> in his Circulation hath fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the principles of nature; therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> have done ſo in their Diſcourſes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 3.</hi> Government according to the Ancients is of three kinds; the government of one man, or of the better ſort, or of the whole People: which by their more learned Names are called Monarchy, Ariſtocracy,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116051:13"/> 
                  <hi>and</hi> Democracy. Legiſlators having found theſe three Governments at beſt to be naught, have invented ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſiſting of a mixture of them all which only is good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The partition of Government, with reference to the perſons in whoſe hands it is, into Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and Democracy, without Queſtion is very natural; for neceſſarily either One or All, or ſome number between both muſt have the power; nor do I ſee how we can have a Conception of any other Government, unleſs at the ſame time we can conceive the power may be reſident in more then All, or leſs then One. It is not to be denied but that in Hiſtory the names of Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and Democracy are to be found applied to ſuch go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, the parts of which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally taken may ſerve to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a new individual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116051:13"/> differing from all of them: But this Mixture and Difference is no more then this (which not being enough attended to, hath been the cauſe of great Miſtakes) that ſome points of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are adminiſtred by one or few perſons, or by the body of the people; as perhaps one ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon governs the Militia, ſome ſelect few diſpatch affairs of State, the whole people meet for Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Officers; And yet the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty or ſupreme power belongs but to one of theſe three; and the Actions in which it is truly ſeated are no waies communicable to the other two.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 3.</hi> The Principles of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are twofold; the goods of the Mind, and the goods of Fortune. The goods of the mind are natural or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired virtues, as Wiſdome, Courage, &amp;c. The goods of Fortune are Riches. To the goods of Mind, anſwers Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116051:14"/> to the goods of Fortune, Power or Empire.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In conſidering the Principles of Government, Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> gives us cauſe to complain of a great Diſappointment; We hoped to receive from his hand that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction about them, which ſeveral great Wits have in vain ſtudied to derive to us; but we find him inſtead of the firſt principles thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting upon us ſuch things as are at beſt but fair endowments of perſons fit to be intruſted with a Government already ſettled or reſolved on. The Wiſdome, Courage, or Riches of another man can never give him a Title to my obedience, nor take from me that liberty with which I was born: There muſt be ſomething before all theſe in the Nature of Government, without which it will be as unjuſt to define Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and ſubjection, as it would
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116051:14"/> be to oblige Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> to give his cloaths or money to the next man he meets wiſer or richer then himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 4.</hi> Empire is of two kinds; Domeſtick and National; or Forraign and Provincial. Domeſtick Empire is founded on Dominion.</p>
               <p>Dominion is Propriety Reall or Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, that is to ſay, in Lands, or in money and goods.</p>
               <p>Lands are held by the Proprietors in ſome Proportion; and ſuch as is the Proportion or Ballance of Dominion or Property in Land, ſuch is the nature of the Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 5.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto Propriety producing Empire it is required that it ſhould have ſome certain root or foothold, which except in Land, it cannot have, being otherwiſe as it were upon the Wing.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs in ſuch Cities as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt moſt by Trade and have little or no land, as <hi>Holland</hi>and <hi>Genoa,</hi> the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116051:15"/> Ballance of treaſure may be equal to that of Land.</p>
            </q>
            <p>There is a great Contention between <hi>Leviathan</hi> and <hi>Oceana</hi> (whoſe names might ſeem to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a better Agreement) whether power or propriety be the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Dominion; but they ſeem to me to mean the ſame things; For what is propriety but Riches? and Riches are <hi>(Pag.</hi> 3.) confeſt to be power: The Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence then is only in Words; and propriety the Ballance; the <hi>Agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> &amp;c. make up onely a new Lexicon to expreſs thoſe things we knew before.</p>
            <p>But the Aſſertion will appear too poſitive that propriety produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Empire conſiſts only in land, except in ſuch places as <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Genoa</hi> which have little or no land: Experience inſtructs us that it is not a large poſſeſſion in lands, but an Eſtate in ready mony
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116051:15"/> which is proper for carrying on a great and ſudden Enterpriſe. And we know of what importance <hi>Banks</hi> or <hi>Monti</hi> are, even in other places beſides <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa.</hi> I will propoſe a Caſe, which was once ſo neer being a true one, that I preſume it canot be rejected as improbable. <hi>England</hi> is defined to have been under the Gothick Ballance, that is, having the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the hands of a Nobility and Clergy, and conſequently to have been a mixt Monarchy, where the King was not abſolute: To a King of <hi>England, Hen.</hi> 7. was the firſt propoſition of diſcovering <hi>America</hi> made by <hi>Columbus,</hi> which if it had been embraced, the Silver of <hi>Potoſi</hi> had ſailed up the <hi>Thames</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Guadalquivir,</hi> and by this the Kings Revenue would <hi>annually</hi> have been encreaſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a <hi>Million,</hi> the reſt comming into the hands of private Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116051:16"/> and Adventurers, and not of the principall Nobility. In this caſe I aſk whether this Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Revenue would not have preponderated on the Kings part, and changed the Ballance, though the Lands at home had ſtill been poſſeſt by the Nobility in the ſame Proportion as before. It is not to be doubted but that a Revenue ſufficient to maintain a Force able to bear down all Oppoſition, does equally conduce to Empire, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ariſes from the Rents of lands, the Profits of ready moneys, the Duties payable upon Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures and Traffique, or any other kind of Income.</p>
            <p>That Empire is well divided into National and Provincial, ſhall be admitted without Oppoſition, if I may be ſatisfied in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, whether there may not be a mixture of theſe two, by which the Ballance of Government ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116051:16"/> receive Alteration: which in effect differs little from this, That the ſeverall parts of a Nationall Empire may ſo poiſe one another as to produce a new Ballance. For example, The Crowns of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Arragon</hi> were of a differing Ballance, the power of the King being more abſolute in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and the intereſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty greater in the latter; The union of theſe two Crowns did not render the Government of <hi>Arragon</hi> purely forrain or provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial; And yet the Ballance in <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> hath been ſo far changed by it, that the power of the King hath devoured the Intereſt of the people. This is no nice and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſpeculation; for it is the caſe of almoſt all the preſent Soveraignties in <hi>Europe,</hi> hardly any one of which is all of one piece, but is compoſed of diſtinct Provinces differing in Genius,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116051:17"/> Laws, Cuſtomes and Ballance, which have come to be united at diſtant times, and by as various Titles.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 10.</hi> Saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> there is an evill which I have ſeen under the Sun which proceedeth from the Ruler; and <hi>Eccleſ. 10. 15.</hi> Sad complaints, that the Principle of Power, and of Authority do not twine in the wreath of Empire. Wherefore, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I know not how it comes about, but Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath taken up a very great unkindneſſe for the Clergy, which (though it be moſt diſcovered towards the end of the book, and in another little Diſcourſe of a later Date) here begins to manifeſt it ſelf: For he invades one part of their Office without aſking their leave; He falls a preaching, and taking that of <hi>Solomon</hi> for his Text, <hi>I have ſeen ſervants upon horſes, &amp;c.</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to make us a very goodly Sermon.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116051:17"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Pag. 10.</hi> &amp; <hi>11.</hi> The ſoul of man is Miſtreſſe of two potent Rivals, the one Reaſon, the other Paſſion, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>From thence he ſlips into ſome Metaphyſical conſiderations of the ſoul of Man, and its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which being tranſlated to Government muſt evince the Truth of this Aſſertion, That a Commonwealth is an Empire of Laws and not of men. If I could be perſwaded he were ſo far in earneſt as to expect any Man ſhould be convinced by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical uſe of two or three Words, ſome further conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might be propoſed; In the mean while it is enough to deſire, that ſeeing the whole force of the Argument reſts upon the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Government with the ſoul of Man, we may be inſtructed what the ſoul is, and what the whole Philoſophy belonging to it: And then and not before, will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116051:18"/> it be time to conſider how far the ſimilitude between that and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will hold true.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 12.</hi> There is a Reaſon which is the Intereſt of Mankind, or of the whole. Now if we ſee even in thoſe Natural Agents, &amp;c. <hi>Hooker B. 1.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The Argumentation about the Reaſon or Intereſt of Mankind is little leſs infirm: For the Queſtion being, Whether there be any ſuch primary Intereſt of Mankind dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Man, He takes it for granted there is ſuch a common right or Intereſt, more excellent then that of the parts, without proffering any other proof then the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of <hi>Hooker</hi> and <hi>Grotius;</hi> Whoſe Opinions cannot oblige us beyond the Reaſons on which they are founded. Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Expreſſions are altogether figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and it is eaſier to prove from them that Things wanting ſenſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116051:18"/> make Diſcourſes and act by Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then that there is ſuch a thing as a common Intereſt of Mankind. For <hi>Grotius</hi> his words, They carry a great Reſtriction with them, and the way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Action in Beaſts is ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Emanation of humane Reaſon, that the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from one to the other muſt needs be very weak.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 12 and 13.</hi> But it may be ſaid the Difficulty remains yet; for be the Intereſt of Popular government right Reaſon, a man doth not look upon Reaſon as it is right or wrong in it ſelf, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And therefore it was a very judicious part to foreſee that the <hi>Difficulty would ſtill remain,</hi> and no leſs ingeniouſly done to confeſſe <hi>That a man doth not look upon reaſon as it is right in it ſelf, but as it makes for him or againſt him;</hi> That is, that the common Intereſt ſtoops
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116051:19"/> to every mans peculiar one. But we are promiſed a ſolution ſo facile, that it is obvious to ſuch as have the Green ſickneſſe. <hi>Let two Girles,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>have a Cake given between them, that each may have what is due: Divide ſaies the one that I may chooſe, or I will divide and you ſhall chooſe; And this is the whole myſtery of a Commonwealth.</hi> An Oven it ſeems is the beſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of the World, and a Bake-houſe the only School of Policy. Let us obey Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> when he ſend us <hi>in Piſtrinam,</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a while this myſtery. The Cake was given that each might have what was due; ſo the Laws of this ſociety proceeded not from any Natural Right, or from the conſent of the Girles, but were limited by the Perſon who gave the Cake with this intent that it might be equally divided between them. Again, theſe Girles live
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116051:19"/> under the Diſcipline of the Rod, that is, under a Government al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready eſtabliſht, and ſhe that had been wronged in the Diviſion might upon appeal to the School Miſtreſs or the Perſon who gave them the Cake, have obtained an equal ſhare. But now ſuppoſe the two girles had met by chance, and found the Cake in their way, and ſuppoſe them out of the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all ſuch perſons whoſe power might conſtrain them to an equal Diviſion, muſt we ſtill believe they would have ſtrained courteſie, and not rather think the ſtronger of the two Girles would have eaten up the whole Cake if ſhe found her ſtomach ſerve her for it? This is no great myſtery, but will be found to be the true Caſe of a Common wealth: For ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Government is founded upon Paternity and the Natural Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the firſt Father had over
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116051:20"/> all the reſt of Mankind who were his ſons, and then there will be no ſuch thing as dividing and chooſing, but being content with what portion he allows; Or elſe Government flows from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſtrength and power in ſome Man or Men to whoſe Will the reſt ſubmit, that by their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they may avoid ſuch miſchief as otherwiſe would be brought upon them; And then here alſo there is no room for dividing and chooſing, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcing in the Will of him whoſe power cannot be reſiſted. There may perhaps be degrees of this power as it more or leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the ſtrength and force of thoſe who are to obey, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of which degrees being duly obſerved will I conceive teach us the true Nature of thoſe things which are commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be Conditions impoſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116051:20"/> upon the ſupream power. If the power of the Government exceed in any great proportion the power of thoſe that are under his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſo that he ſtands not in need of any thing he can have from them, The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment becomes abſolute and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited; But if he exceeds them in a leſs proportion and be in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual want of ſomething that they may allow him, he muſt buy it by ſome conceſſions or other as cheap as he can; But this amounts not to a mixture of the Government; for without an exceſs in Power there can be no Government. Thus a General of an Army ſitting down before two Towns, the one very weak, the other of good ſtrength, will have the firſt at diſcretion, to the ſecond he allows good and honourable Conditions, out of a deſire to ſave his time or Men, or to preſerve the place from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116051:21"/> being defaced, and the Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imbezeled: Or to take Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s own example, The ſtronger Girle gives the other a piece of Cake to fetch her ſome water to drinke after it. Since Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath brought theſe Actors upon the Stage, he will not I hope take it ill if one of the Girles give him an Anſwer; and tell him in her proper ſtyle, <hi>That his Cake is dough.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 13.</hi> A Commonwealth is but a Civill ſociety of men: Let us take twenty men, and forthwith make a Commonwealth; ſix of theſe will be wiſer then the other fourteen, and by the eminency of their Parts acquire an influence, that is, <hi>Authoritas Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum.</hi> Wherefore this can be no other then a Natural Ariſtocracy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by God throughout the whole body of Mankind.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In the next example of the twenty men, the Paralogiſm lies
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116051:21"/> in this. <hi>Let us take twenty men, ſaies he, and forthwith make a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;</hi> He firſt ſuppoſes them a Commonwealth, and then conſiders how they would diſpoſe of the Government; But it is to be denied that they could ever have been a Commonwealth, unleſs in one of the caſes laſt expreſt, in which the Government would not have been free for them to diſpoſe of. The ſence of want among Men that are in equality of power, may beget a deſire of Exchange; as let me have your Horſe and you ſhall have my Cow, which is the Fountain of private Contracts; but it is not to be with reaſon imagined that this ſhould be enough to make a Man part with a natural Freedom, and put himſelf into the hands of a Power from which he can after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward have no ſhield though it ſhould be uſed to his own Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116051:22"/>
            <p> But Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath not in this loſt his way without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; for I have obſerved very frequently that while men profeſs to conſider of the Principles of Government, they fall upon Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are the meer Effects of Government, not unlike the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Grotius,</hi> that they who treat of <hi>Jus Gentium</hi> do commonly miſtake ſome part of the Roman <hi>Jus Civile</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>To conſider this inſtance of the twenty men a little further. What ſecurity can Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> give us, that the ſix in their conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall not aim rather at their own advantage then that of the fourteen, and ſo make uſe of the eminence of their parts to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the reſt? Or on the other fide how ſhall we be ſatisfied that the fourteen will not ſoon begin to think themſelves wiſe enough to conſult too, and making uſe of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116051:22"/> their exceſs in power pull the fix off their Cuſhions, where they muſt needs appear to ſit at better Eaſe then the fourteen were in while they ſtood at the Door waiting for the Reſult of their Debates.</p>
            <p>I am willing to gratifie Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> with his Partition of them into ſix and fourteen; but if I had been in an humour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, it had been as free for me to have ſaid that ſome one of the <hi>twenty</hi> would have excelled all the reſt in Judgement, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, Courage and height of <hi>Genius,</hi> and then told him that had been a Naturall <hi>Monarchy</hi> eſtabliſh't by God himſelfe over Mankind.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 14.</hi> The Decrees of the Senate are never Laws, nor ſo called, but <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natuſconſulta.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>In exchange of this fair dealing, I expect Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> ſhould
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116051:23"/> inform me what it is he means when he ſaies the Decrees of the Senate are never Laws, nor ſo called, but <hi>Senatus conſulta;</hi> The word <hi>Senatus conſultum</hi> is a Latine name, and belongs not properly to the Decrees of any Senate but that of the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo I muſt at preſent neceſſarily underſtand him, That the Roman <hi>Senatus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulta</hi> never were Laws. It is true they were not called <hi>Leges,</hi> no more were the <hi>Plebiſcita,</hi> the <hi>Edicta Praetorum,</hi> and other parts of the Roman <hi>Jus Civile;</hi> but they had the power of Laws, and equally with them required the obedience of the whole Roman people. <hi>Coepit Senatus ſe interponere, &amp; quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid conſtituiſſet, obſervabatur; Id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. de ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine juris. P. neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde quia.</note> 
               <hi>jus appellabatur Senatus conſultum.</hi> Thus the <hi>Senatus conſultum Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donianum,</hi> with many more came to have a place allowed them by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> in the compilement of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116051:23"/> the Roman Laws. Nor can it be pretended that the <hi>Senatus conſulta</hi> were (like the orders of one ſingle houſe of Parliament) binding only to their own members; for though it were ſo at firſt with the <hi>Plebiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita,</hi> to avoid the diſcord which was by it occaſioned, It was ſoon agreed that the diſtinct Decrees of the Senate and People ſhould be extended to the Nature of Laws, and oblige the whole body <note place="margin">Cujac. com. ad. s.</note> of the Commonwealth, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Cujacius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To lay down what hath been ſaid upon a ſmaller Scale: It hath been ſhown, That Ancient Prudence differs not from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, and ſerves not at all to enforce <hi>Oceana</hi>'s project of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; That Commonwealths are no more then Monarchys the Empire of Laws and not of Men; That there is no ſuch thing as a mixt Government, but that the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116051:24"/> ſupreme Power and the Actions in which it truly and properly reſides muſt belong to one or all or ſome Number between both; That <hi>Oceana</hi> falls ſhort in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the principles of government, and takes for Principles things that are a great deal on this ſide of them; That to ſay propriety is the foundation of Empire is all one to ſay that power is; That this propriety may as well conſiſt in ready Money, or any other forraign Revenue as in Poſſeſſion of Lands; That there is a Ballance producible by diſtinct Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment united into one perſon, which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> did not conſider; That the common Right or Intereſt of Mankind, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Man, is not firmly made out to us; That the notion of dividing and chooſing cannot ſubſiſt; And that the Inſtances alledged for it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116051:24"/> are miſtaken; That the conſent of the people is an improbable and weak Hypotheſis of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of Government, which is better deduced either from Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Force; And finally that there can be no Government without exceſs of power.</p>
            <p>After this I hope it will appear no ill grounded confidence in me to ſay, that there is very little, if any thing, of conſequence in the firſt and General part of the Preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries left unanſwered: And the principal Stones being thus taken from the Foundation, a little Wind will be enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe the ſuperſtructure.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 15.</hi> Now whether I have rightly tranſcribed theſe Principles of a Commonwealth out of Nature, I ſhall appeal unto God, and to the World. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto God in the Fabrick of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And unto the World in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſeries of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Prudence.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116051:25"/>
            <p> I am now come to Mr. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Appeal to paſt Ages for juſtifying theſe Principles of a Commonwealth; which Appeal is made to <hi>God in the Fabrick of the Commonwealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and unto the World in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſeries of Ancient Prudence.</hi> Of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> anon; For the World I muſt remind Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> of my juſt complaint put in againſt him for partiality in omitting the Examples of the <hi>Aſſyrians, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and all other old Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, which certainly are included in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſeries of Ancient Prudence.</hi> But perhaps I am too blame to think Mr. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſhould have leſſe Diſcretion then a common Atturney, who will be ſure to examine only thoſe Witneſſes that ſeem to make for the cauſe in which he is enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116051:25"/>
            <p> One particular in this appears more then ſtrange to me; It is, that having ſaid the Heathens have all written their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, as if they had no other Copy but that of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the holy Scriptures, <hi>(Page</hi> 18) in the Enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration he brings in <hi>Switz</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> Which is it? Are theſe two within the ſeries of Ancient Prudence, or muſt they be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among the Heathen Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths?</p>
            <p>I applied my ſelf ſo late to the reading and conſidering of <hi>Oceana,</hi> that before I could reach ſo far as to examine what is aſſerted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I was made a ſpectatour of the Paper-combat between the Author and Dr. <hi>Ferne,</hi> the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of which proclaims the Author's conceit of the Victory. He indeed deſerves the reputation of making rude Charges, and in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116051:26"/> theſe Diſputes the laſt Reply gains the Opinion of the ſame Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, as in Battels it does to ſtay laſt upon the Field. If the Doctor's Leiſure and Inclination ſerves him, we may ſee the Fight renewed; However there is ſo much reaſon to expect that ſome of the Clergy (againſt all of whom the Author hath declared War) will undertake the Quarrel, that I think it cannot juſtly be counted any ſubterfuge in me to wave this part of the Diſpute, and leave it in the hands of thoſe men whoſe Intereſt and Obligation gives them a propriety in it.</p>
            <p>Not to examine then whether it be a true or falſe Picture which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath drawn of the Republique of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I will only conſider how far we are now bound to work after that Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and whether there may not be Proportion, Force and Beauty in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116051:26"/> the Face of Government, though it differs from the Air of that of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And this the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſeems propoſed with more Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity then belongs to a bare Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Chriſtian World accuſed of blindneſs or negligence <hi>(Page</hi> 18) for not tranſcribing from it.</p>
            <p>It muſt not be denied but that whatſoever ſhall appear to have been an eſtabliſhment of God in the Jewiſh Republique, is to be allowed conſonant to the Laws of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> de jure bel. &amp; pac. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Nature, Juſtice and Wiſedome; ſeeing a Legiſlator ſupremely Good, Juſt and Wiſe, cannot be ſuppoſed to have made Laws which do not bear the impreſſion and character of that hand from which they proceed. Yet if we ſhould admit of Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s Poſition that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had the power of confirming all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116051:27"/> their Laws, ſo that without their conſent they had not <hi>(Page</hi> 16 and 17) been Laws, We muſt abate much of the precedent Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for it is a great deal leſs to be the Adviſer or Perſwader of a thing then to be the Author and Commander of it. He inſtances in this power of the people in that Act where they make God King, <hi>Exodus</hi> 19. So that in his Opinion the Laws given in that and the next Chapters (for they are but a continuation of the ſame Action) take their validity from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, who had a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of diſſenting by which they might have exempted from thoſe Laws. Theſe Laws are the Ten Commandements, and if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> need not have been ſubjected to them without their own conſents, there is no reaſon but we ſhould enjoy the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge. In this Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116051:27"/> proves an huge benefactour to Mankind; for he hath with no greater expence then the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their conſents aſſerted them into the mighty Liberty of being free from the whole Morall Law. But I aſk pardon for this Digreſſion, and come to another conſideration of the influence of the Jewiſh conſtitutions upon our practiſe.</p>
            <p>It is now lawful in making of Laws and modelling a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to tread in the ſteps of <hi>Moſes</hi> unleſs in ſuch things as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their own Nature termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with the Revelation of the Goſpel, or have been altered by ſome general or ſpecial conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Beyond theſe conſiderations I am not aware of any prerogative of Authority belonging to the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> more then any other Republique: For a Law can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116051:28"/> onely thoſe to whom it is given, which were the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> only; And as no other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was at that time (according to the opinion of the ſoberer of the Jews themſelves) bound to obſerve the Jewiſh Laws or form of Government; ſo it would be much more unreaſonable at this diſtance of time and place, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon us any Obligation of following either their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or their Laws. In conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Laws and frames of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it is not enough to look at the Dignity of the Legiſlator, but regard muſt be had alſo to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of times, places, and perſons, with which the Lawgiver is often ſo fettered that he cannot take thoſe Reſolutions which in themſelves are beſt. Now there were many conditions and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vaſtly differing from the preſent
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116051:28"/> Age, ſome of which I ſhall have occaſion to touch when I ſpeak of the <hi>Agrarian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I will not conceal the pleaſure I have taken in obſerving that though Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes a great Enmity to Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> his politiques, underhand not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he holds a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with him, and does ſilently ſwallow down ſuch Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> hath chewed for him: Of this ſort is the Fancy of the compact between God and the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by vertue of which he received the Civil Power, and was enabled to enact Laws for them; His conceits taken from the Notation of the Words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are alſo of the ſame breed.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag. 20.</hi> Let me invite Leviathan who of all other Governments giveth the advantage unto Monarchy for Perfection, to a better diſquiſition
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116051:29"/> of it by theſe three Aſſertions.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The invitation ſent to Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> is not I preſume ſo perſonally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to him, but that it may indifferently concern any Man who concurs with him in giving the Advantage for perfection unto <hi>Monarchy</hi> of all other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: In that Propoſition I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelf a <hi>Zelote,</hi> and have <hi>Temerity</hi> enough to expoſe my body to the receiving thoſe <hi>Blows</hi> which were aimed at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> The firſt, (which requireth no proof) That the Perfection of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment lyeth upon ſuch a Libration in the frame of it, that no man nor men, in or under it, can have the Intereſt; or having the intereſt can have the Power to diſturbe it with Sedition.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Though Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> thinks the firſt Aſſertion requires no proof, it may admit of ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116051:29"/> To give ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as no Man nor Men in or under it, can have the Intereſt to diſturb with Sedition, is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether impoſſible; For that were to ſuppoſe there ſhould not be in an whole countrey one Ambitious Boor man who might hope for Advantage, nor one Vicious Rich man who might expect ſecurity from the perturbation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: The whole matter then muſt be reduced to the want of power to doe it. And that will appear to be in no other Libration but this, That the Power of which the Governour is poſſeſſed does ſo vaſtly exceed the power remaining with thoſe who are to obey, that in caſe of a conteſt it muſt be deſperately unreaſonable for them to hope to maintain their Cauſe and Party. The true Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod then of attaining to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Government, is to make the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116051:30"/> Governour abſolute; for if there be any who can Diſpute upon probable Terms the power with him, the State can never be free from Tumult and Sedition.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> The ſecond, That Monarchy reaching the Perfection of the kind, reacheth not unto the Perfection of Government, but muſt have ſome dangerous flaw in it. For proof of this</p>
               <p>Monarchy is either by Arms or by a Nobility: A Monarchy by Arms, as that of the Turk, hath this incurable Flaw, That the <hi>Janizaries</hi> have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Intereſt and perpetual Power to raiſe ſedition, and tear the Prince himſelf in Pieces. In a Monarchy by a Nobility, (as of late in <hi>Oceana)</hi> the flaw is this, that the Nobility had frequent Intereſt and Perpetual power by their Retainers and Tenants to raiſe ſedition, and to levy a laſting War. Wherefore neither of theſe is a perfect Government.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116051:30"/>
            <p> But this is not attainable in a Monarchy, ſaies Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s ſecond Aſſertion; For a King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a ſingle Perſon, that kind of Government hath this Flaw in it, that the Inſtruments of Ruling whether they be an Army or a Nobility, have both intereſt and power to diſturb the government; for the proof of which the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>Oceana</hi> are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>In a Monarchy by Arms it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed very apparent that the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies of the <hi>Soldateſca</hi> are always dangerous, and often Fatall; But then they happen ſolely among the Militia of the Court; for the Troops diſperſed through the Provinces (upon whom the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Government depends) can ſeldome, perhaps never, be ſhown to have cauſed ſuch Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; And yet ſuch a Militia at Court ſeems neceſſary for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116051:31"/> of the Prince's perſon, and the Reputation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: But it will not be hard to find a Temperament, by which all may be ſecured, which I think will lie in this, That the Guards of the King's perſon be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed beyond neceſſity of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that they be not ſuffered to ſtagnate at Court, but be by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual circulation drawn out upon ſervice, and chiefly that they conſiſt not of one intire Body united under the ſame Head, but be divided into diſtinct Parties and Commands: As we may ſee in <hi>France,</hi> where though (in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the extent of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions) the Kings Guards be more numerous then thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperours; yet being divided into the diſtinct Bodies of <hi>French, Scotch</hi> and <hi>Switz</hi> Guards, under their ſeveral Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels and Captains, they have never
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116051:31"/> been the Authors of any the leaſt Sedition. And in <hi>Turky</hi> of late years they begin to learn the Art of poiſing the <hi>Janizaries</hi> by the <hi>Spahis,</hi> and ſo have frequently evaded the danger of their Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies.</p>
            <p>In like manner in Monarchy by a Nobility, there never ariſes any Danger to the Crown, but when either a great part of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power is put into the hands of the Nobility as in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> or when ſome Perſon or Family is ſuffered to overtop the reſt in Riches, Commands, and Dependance, as Princes of the blood and <hi>Lorrain</hi> not long ſince in <hi>France,</hi> and of old the <hi>Montforts</hi> and the <hi>Nevils</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> The firſt is a vicious conſtitution of the Government, and a Monarchy only in name; the ſecond eaſily admits of this cure, That theſe Great Ones be reduced to a leſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116051:32"/> volumn, and levell'd into an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with the reſt of their Order.</p>
            <p>But I ſee no Neceſſity of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Diviſion of Monarchies which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath made, when the moſt Natural and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent form of Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ariſes from the Mixture of them both. The Prince who governs meerly by an Army, not only is expoſed to the danger of their Mutinies, but is alſo forced to run this hazard, That up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any potent Invaſion, the loſs of a Battel or two draws inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly along with it the loſſe of his Crown: On the other ſide he that reſts wholy upon a Nobilty, leaves himſelf in a manner at their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and is with no great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty Diſpoſſeſt of the Throne. Let me then have leave to aſſert that the perfection of Monarchy is free from thoſe flaws which are charged upon it, and that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116051:32"/> in Governing by a Nobility weighty enough to keep the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under; yet not tall enough, in any particular perſon, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with the Prince; And by a moderate Army kept up under the Notion of Guards and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which may be ſufficient to ſtrangle all Seditions in the Cradle.</p>
            <p>In this place it will be no great impertinence to deſire to know of Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> his Opinion of the Way of Governing by Councels, which I confeſſe I have alwaies thought admirable; I do not mean ſuch as are coordinate with the Prince, (which have been ſeen in the World) but ſuch as thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> purely of Advice and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, with power only to inform and perſwade, not limit the Princes Will: For almoſt all the weakneſſes which have been thought incident to Monarchy,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116051:33"/> are by this courſe prevented, and if there be any ſteadineſs and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity in the Senate of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, this takes it all in. If the Delays of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Councels be objected, the anſwer is obvious, that they proceed more from the grave retired temper of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Nation, then from the Nature of theſe Councels; And this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is much more forcible againſt all Popular Governments.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 20. and 21.</hi> The third, that Popular Government reaching the Perfection of the kind, reacheth the Perfection of Government, and hath no flaw in it, for which kind of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution I have ſomething more to ſay then Leviathan hath ſaid, or ever will be able to ſay for Monarchy; As</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1.</hi> That it is the Government was never conquered by any Monarch, from the beginning of the World unto this day; for if the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116051:33"/> of <hi>Greece</hi> came under the yoak of the Kings of <hi>Macedon,</hi> they were firſt broken by themſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The third Aſſertion remains, which ſhall receive a Diſcuſſion through all the five Branches of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt of which ſeems intended for a tryal of our Noſes, whether they will ſerve us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Fallacy of an Inference from the proſperous ſucceſſe of Arms, to the Perfection of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: As if on the one ſide great and well policed Empires had not been ſubverted by people ſo eloigned from the perfection of government, that we ſcarce know of any thing to tie them together but the deſire of Booty; And on the other ſide we had not the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the little Republiques of <hi>Raguſa</hi> and <hi>San Marino,</hi> which are commended for their upright and equal frame of Government, and yet have hardly extended
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116051:34"/> their Dominions beyond the ſize of an handſome Mannour. It is not the perfection of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the populoſity of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the natural Valour of the Inhabitants, the Abundance of Horſes, Arms, and other things neceſſary for the equipping of an Army, aſſiſted with a good Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Diſcipline, that Quality a people for Conqueſt; And where theſe concur, Victory is intailed upon them, whether it be of one Monarch over another, or of a Commonwealth over a people of the ſame form of Government. Nay, I will add of a Monarch over a Commonwealth, though Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath pawn'd his Credit that this was never known <hi>from the beginning of the World unto this day.</hi> He foreſaw the inſtance that might be made of the Kings of <hi>Macedon</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Commonwealths of <hi>Greece,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d therefore would
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116051:34"/> have us believe that had not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if they had <hi>not been firſt broken by themſelves;</hi> At this rate of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> ſhal have much adoe to produce any one Feat of Arms of a Commonwealth, which will not be eaſily ſtrip't of it's Glory by attributing the ſucceſſe to ſome Miſcarriage or Diſorder of the Enemy. And it is worth obſerving, that to evade the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rce of this Inſtance, He admits of ſomthing in the Commonwealths of <hi>Greece</hi> that will evince them to have been of a turbulent mutinous Temper, &amp; ignorant of their true Intereſt. But to help a bad Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, let me aſk Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> what he thinks of the little <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Republiques planted round the coaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Aſia Minor,</hi> and of the ſervitude into which they were brought firſt by the <hi>Lydian,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pauſan. meſſen.</note> and then by the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchs, the aſſerting whoſe Liberties was
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116051:35"/> the moſt plauſible pretence the other <hi>Greeks</hi> had for the <hi>Perſian</hi> War? What account likewiſe is to be given of the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, which (before that the Iſland came under the Power of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> and <hi>Romans)</hi> were reduced under the yoak of one Monarch? And, not to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the obſcure Paths of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, let me beg his judgement of the Commonwealth of <hi>Genua,</hi> which fell under the Dominion of the Dukes of <hi>Milan,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (upon pretence of their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) of the Kings of <hi>France.</hi> If it be told me that this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſubſiſts to this day, I ſhall only need to reply that <hi>Andrew Doria</hi> did rather erect a new then reſtore an old Republique, (as will appear by the alterations he made in the Laws and Form of the old Government) and that it is altogether as rational to fortifie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116051:35"/> the claim of the preſent States of <hi>Holland</hi> from the freedom injoyed by the Ancient <hi>Batavians,</hi> as to pretend that the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths of <hi>Genua</hi> is the ſame with what it was before it paid obedience to the Dukes of <hi>Milan.</hi> I will afflict Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> but with one particular more, and that is of the <hi>Florentine</hi> Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, which having chaſed away all of the Family of <hi>Medici,</hi> and reſtored it ſelf to a plenary Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, was by the Arms of <hi>Charles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Guicciard. lib. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> under the Command firſt of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and then of <hi>Don Ferrando Gonzaga,</hi> forced to ſubmit to that Monarchical Government which it now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 21. 2.</hi> That it is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that hath frequently led mighty Monarchs in Triumph.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond Mr. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> runs upon the Foile, it being
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116051:36"/> only the converſion of the Firſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid 3.</hi> That it is the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve been ſeditions, it hath not been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom any imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the kind, but in the particular Conſtitution, which where ever the like hath happened, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt have been unequal.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="3">3. The third Branch is, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, a very pleaſant One, and not unlike the Procedure of the judiciary Aſtrologers; Who grounding their Art upon wild and Arbitray, but as they pretend, infallible Notions, are fain to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the ſucceſſe of ſome few lucky Predictions; And when theſe are confronted with the foul and ridiculous Miſtakes of the greateſt Maſters of their Art, They preſently ſhelter themſelves under this anſwer, That the Error is not in the rules of Art but in the Man, who therefore is convinced to have miſtaken in his calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116051:36"/> becauſe his Predictions have not been juſtifyed by the Event. So if we complain of the ſeditions which have infeſted almoſt all Commonwealths that ever were, Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> tels us, <hi>It hath not been from any imperfection in the kind, but in the particular Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which where ever the like hath happened muſt have been unequall.</hi> For my part I deſpair of cutting off the Retreat, and think him to be dealt with only by thoſe who know how to drive the <hi>Iriſh</hi> from a Bog.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid. 4.</hi> That it is the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which if it have been any thing near equal was never ſeditious; or let him ſhew me what ſedition hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> or <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p n="4">4. We ſhall have ſomewhat firmer footing in the Next, in which the Commonwealths of <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> are brought upon the Carpet for ſuch as by the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116051:37"/> equality of their Government have been redeemed from all Seditions. Of <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> firſt.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> hath enjoyed a more then ordinary exemption from Domeſtick Troubles, it is upon the ſame Accou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t that he that works his Horſe hard and gives him no Provender is ſecure of being run away with: The deſign of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> in framing their Laws ſeems only to have lookt at making them good Souldiers, and accordingly they were ſeldome free from War, and when they were, the hardneſſe of their Diet, <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Licurg.</note> the ſtrictneſſe of their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Toyl of their Sports and Exerciſes made Peace it ſelf little leſſe rigorous then War uſes to be, The greateſt landed man in the whole Countrey had not enough to maintain a Teme, and for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Eſtate, all but Iron money being prohibited, what would
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116051:37"/> now go into one of our little Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, with them would have loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Waggon; Riches, Luxury and Exceſſe, being thus baniſhed, it is no wonder they continued quiet, ſeeing there was nothing left for which they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; the condition of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Spartan</hi> being in every point (bating meerly the Reputation of Power) as deſirable as that of their Kings. And yet even thus they did not ſcape.</p>
            <p>For firſt, They were infeſted with frequent and dangerous ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levations of their Helots or ſlaves; Theſe Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath no reaſon to call external Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>(Page</hi> 167.) being the Helots were not ſtrangers but inhabitants and ſpread over the Face of the whole Countrey; Nay more, They were Fundamental and Eſſential to the Commonwealth; For the <hi>Spartans</hi> were by their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116051:38"/> Laws and Inſtitution to neglect all Occupations, even Agriculture it ſelf, and attend ſolely to the ſervice of the Publique, which could not poſſibly have been done unleſſe they had had the Helots to perform thoſe Offices.</p>
            <p>And then have they often been in diſtractions about the ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Crown, ſome of which it will be proper to relate. A quarrel breaking out between the two Kings <hi>Cleomenes</hi> and <hi>Demara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> the latter was accuſed of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardy, and as it was then the cuſtome of <hi>Greece</hi> in difficult caſes, a reference is made to the Oracle <note place="margin">Pauſan. Lacon.</note> at <hi>Delphos,</hi> which having been bribed by <hi>Cleomenes,</hi> pronounces againſt <hi>Demaratus,</hi> who thereupon is depoſed and ſeeks Protection from the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice not only of the <hi>Laconian,</hi> but of the whole <hi>Grecian</hi> Intereſt. Of the ſame nature was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116051:38"/> about the ſucceſſion, when by the power of <hi>Lyſander</hi> and his faction <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to the Crown, with the <note place="margin">Plutar. Ageſil.</note> Excluſion of <hi>Leotychides</hi> the true heir. But much more Fatall was the conteſt between <hi>Cleonymus</hi> and his Nephew <hi>Arens</hi> the ſon of <hi>Acro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus,</hi> who being <hi>Jure Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis</hi> (as the Modern Lawyers ſpeak) preferred before him, <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus</hi> made ſhift to get ſome forces together with which he gave beginning to a civil War in which the City <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rax</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and which was far worſe <note place="margin">Pauſan. Lacon. Plutarch. Pyrr.</note> he drew King <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> into the Countrey, who made himſelfe Maſter of the <hi>Campagna,</hi> beſieged the capital City, and reduced the Commonwealth to the laſt Gaſp. The Reign of <hi>Agis</hi> and <hi>Cleomenes</hi> were ſo full of Turbulency and Sedition, that it is ſufficient to name them.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116051:39"/>
            <p> Nor have they been priviledged from another ſort of Attempts, which being ſecretly managed by ſome few Conſpirators diſcover not themſelves till the danger be almoſt inevitable; This will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Treaſon contrived in the beginning of <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> reign, at <note place="margin">Xenoph. Gr. Hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> which time the Republique was in its greateſt health and vigour at home and higheſt Reputation abroad; The Author of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy waa one <hi>Cinadon</hi> a bold gallant young fellow who excited by ambition was reſolved to make himſelf Maſter of the State, and had engaged in the Deſign divers Perſons of courage and execution, provided them with Arms, and had prepared all things ready to fall upon the King, the <hi>Ephori</hi> and the Senate in the Market-place, which being done He made no doubt by a plauſible Declaration to draw over to his Party the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:116051:39"/> ſlaves, the mean People and the Borderers. Things were at this Paſſe when one of the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors revealed all to the <hi>Ephori,</hi> by whoſe extraordinary Wiſedome and conduct the Heads of the Party were ſurpriſed, and the Deſign broke in pieces. The practiſe of <hi>Lyſander</hi> for altering the Government ſhall not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on; for though the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance was admirable, yet the Diſcovery having been prevented by his Death, it will not be amiſſe to let it ſleep with him.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Venice</hi> is poſſeſt, by Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s own confeſſion, of ſeveral Advantages by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of her ſituation, which ſhe were not to expect from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of her Government; Among theſe there is juſt cauſe to reckon her Immunity from Seditions, which notwithſtanding hath not been ſo intire that we need be put
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116051:40"/> upon any difficulty in the retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Inſtances to prove ſhe hath been ſubject to Tumults and Faction.</p>
            <p>Not to inſiſt upon the continual Diſorders to which ſhe was expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before the ſettlement of the Commonwealth upon the Election of her Dukes, Let <hi>Giannotti</hi> be the computer and from the firſt to <hi>Seba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tian Ciani</hi> the 39<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Duke, We ſhall have an account of three <note place="margin">Donato Giannotti.</note> Dukes meeting with violent Deaths by inteſtine broiles, and of Nine who after having ſuffered Excaecation died in Exile. In the time of Duke <hi>Piero Gradenigo</hi> (under whom the Commonwealth received it's laſt Reiglement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 360 years ago) We meet firſt with <hi>Marrino Boccon</hi> who not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the new conſtitutions to his Guſt endeavoured to opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe them by open Force: But the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of this Attempt is loſt in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:116051:40"/> that more great and dangerous One (which happened alſo in the Reign of the ſame Duke though not till the year 1311) of <hi>Baja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monte Tiepoli,</hi> by which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth was reduced to that Exigence, that the onely hope of her preſervation conſiſted in the well defending the ſtairs of the <note place="margin">Gaſp. Contarim.</note> Palace of St. <hi>Mark.</hi> After that in the year 1355. the Health of the Commonwealth became her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, I mean the power of the Dukes by which ſhe had gained ſo much Order, Grace, and Firmneſs, was made an Inſtrument to the mabition of Duke <hi>Marin Falier</hi> for diſſolving the Frame of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; But at this Time the Power of the <hi>Dieci</hi> was ſalutary to the Republique in the Depoſition and Execution of <hi>Falier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of late days indeed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>Venice</hi> hath enjoyed tranquillity enough at home, (for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116051:41"/> though partialities and factions be kept up between the Old and New families of Noblem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, yet having never made any ſcandalous Eruptions, they do but little harm) for which She is a Debtor to the nice and dangerous Eſtate of her Affairs abroad; On the one ſide She is next Neighbour to the Devouring <hi>Ottomon</hi> Empire, and on the other her Frontire reaches to the Territories of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> a Prince of as good Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite though of a ſlower digeſtion; Nay the <hi>Rope</hi> himſelfe for all his Age and Holineſſe hath often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to commit a Rape upon her: In this condition it is no more wonder that the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a Publique Enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets Union and Concord within her ſelf, then it is to find Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among the Mariners of that Ship which is ready to be boarded by Pirates.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:116051:41"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Pag. 22. 5.</hi> That it is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which attaining unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect equality, hath ſuch a libration in the frame of it, that no man living can ſhew which way any man or men in or under it, can contract ſuch Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or Power as ſhould be able to diſturb the Commonwealth with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; Wherefore an equall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth is that only which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flaw, and containeth in it the full Perfection of Government.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="5">5. After all this in anſwer to the fifth Branch, I will only tell Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> that the Libration He ſpeaks of in Government, is of the ſame Nature with a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Motion in Mechanicks; for as the one is not attainable as long as there is in Matter a reſiſtence to Motion, or a Propenſity in it by which it is determined to ſome other Motion; So will the other be impoſſible as long as Men have private Intereſts and Paſſions by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:116051:42"/> which they are biaſſed from the publique Ends of Government: And as all Motion will grow faint and expire unleſſe renewed by the hand of a continuall Mover; ſo there is no Frame of Laws or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Government which will not decay and come to Ruine unleſſe repaired by the Prudence and Dexterity of thoſe who Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern. Now that this may not be expected from a Monarch as well as from a Senate or any Aſſembly of Men, I have not yet met with any conviction, but rather find it reaſonable to think that where Debates are cleareſt, the Reſults of them moſt ſecret, and the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſudden, (which are the Advantages of a Monarchy) there the Diſorders of a State will ſooneſt be diſcovered, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Remedies beſt applied.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> In an equal Commonwealth there can be no more ſtrife, then there
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:116051:42"/> can be overballance in equal weights; Wherefore the Commonwealth of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> being that which of all others is the moſt equall in the Conſtition, is that wherein there never happened ſtrife between the Senate and the People.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Wherfore it is not this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded equality of a Commonwealth that cauſes her ſtability and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but rather the contrary; For, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>(Page</hi> 5.) where there are two Parties in a Republique with equall power, (as in that of <hi>Rome</hi> the Nobility had one half and the People the other half) Confuſion and Miſery are there entailed: And to avoid this there can be no way but to make the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth very unequal, that is to make the ſcale of Power gravitate on the part of thoſe perſons who are poſſeſſed of the Government. This will be found to be the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:116051:43"/> practiſe of <hi>Venice,</hi> which though alledged as the example of a moſt equall One, is as much as any in the World, an unequal Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; The power there is wholly in the hands of the Noble Families, who make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of about 3000 heads, though formerly they have amounted to 4500, and the people are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it more then that they are admitted to the Offices of Chancellours and Secretary ſhip, which are places of no power though of ſome Truſt: Nor is it material perhaps not true) which Mr. <hi>Harrington (Page</hi> 9.) hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, that the Senate of <hi>Venice</hi> at the firſt Inſtitution took in the whole people; for the Queſtion belongs not to the firſt Original Inſtitution which was rude and not well digeſted, but to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Frame of that Republique a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was perfected under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116051:43"/> of <hi>Piero Gradenigo.</hi> To conclude this point, <hi>Contarini</hi> himſelf a Noble <hi>Venetian</hi> and very likely to diſcern the true temper of their Government, when he enquires into the reaſons of the fidelity of the <hi>Venetian</hi> people to the Senate, never thinks upon this equality in the conſtitution of the Commonwealth, but propoſes the plenty of Bread, the Proviſion made for the poor by ſo many Hoſpitals, the lucrative employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Artificers in the Arſenal, things purely Accidental and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal, as the moſt probable cauſes which can be aſſigned of ſo happy an Effect.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> An equall Commonwealth is ſuch an one as is equall both in her Ballance or foundation, and in the ſuperſtructures, that is to ſay, in her <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law, and in her Rotation.</p>
               <p>An equall <hi>Agrarian</hi> is a perpetual Law eſtabliſhing and preſerving the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:116051:44"/> ballance of Dominion, by ſuch a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution, that no one man or number of men within the compaſſe of the Few or Ariſtocracy, can come to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the whole people by their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Lands.</p>
            </q>
            <p>To him that makes propriety, and that in Lands, the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Empire, the eſtabliſhing an <hi>Agrarian</hi> is of abſolute Neceſſity, that by it the power may be fixt in thoſe hands to whom it was at firſt committed: But if an Eſtate in ready money, or any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue conduces as much to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire as the Poſſeſſion of Lands, (which was ſhown in its Place) the true importance of an <hi>Agrarian</hi> will come to no more but this, that the government be provided of a Revenue ſufficient to make good that advantage of Power which it enjoys over all perſons and parties living under that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The examples of an
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:116051:44"/> 
               <hi>Agrarian</hi> are ſo infrequent that Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> is conſtrained to wave all but two Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, and can find in the whole extent of Hiſtory only <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> to faſten upon. What the Nature of theſe <hi>Agrarians</hi> was, and how they differ from that which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> goes about to eſtabliſh, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be the buſineſſe of my preſent Diſquiſition.</p>
            <p>When in obedience to God's command <hi>Abraham</hi> had abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his native ſoil, and the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of his Fathers, and like an Adventurer in proſecution of his Fortune had wandered as far as the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> He received a promiſe of God in reward of this ſubmiſſion that his poſterity ſhould enjoy as a poſſeſſion the Land in which he now l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved as a ſtranger; The hopes of ſeeing this promiſe performed had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo much influence upon the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:116051:45"/> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that when in <hi>Egyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they fell into an Affliction of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Preſſure and Duration that ever Nation ſuffered, They not onely bore up againſt it by their care in maintaining their National Intereſt, but with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Diligence attended to the preſerving their Genealogies through their Tribes and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: The time of impletion of the Promiſe being come, There was no Man that was able to make out his deſcent from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> by <hi>Jacob,</hi> but had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Title to the Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Land, and conſequently it was neceſſary to divide the Land <hi>viritim</hi> among the people of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Yet it will not be eaſie to determine whether they all inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by equail Portions, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Diviſion reſpect was had to the Princes of Tribes and Heads of Families. The Publique
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:116051:45"/> Diviſion upon the return of the Survey <hi>(Joſ. cap.</hi> 18.) it is evident went no further then to aſſign by lot the Seat of every Tribe, or at moſt of the Families in that Tribe; For the ſhares of particular Men it appears not how they were laid out (unleſſe in the caſes of <hi>Joſhuae</hi> and <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb</hi> which were peculiars) except the place in <hi>Numbers, cap.</hi> 26. 54. belongs to them, <hi>To many thou ſhalt give the more inheritance, and to few thou ſhalt give the leſſe inheritance; to every one ſhall his inheritance be given according to thoſe that were numbred of him.</hi> But it is more probable that this is meant of families then of perſons, if we conſider that the Dignity of the Princes and Heads of Families could not have been preferved without ſome Advantage in Eſtate; And beſides if none could have been Rich, none could have been Poor, and yet we find Poor
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:116051:46"/> abounding in the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> even to that extremity as to addict themſelves into ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. Let the Nature of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Lands be what it will, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are was taken for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people in and upon it; and therefore there could be no alienation of Land but with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feaſance or power of redemption, and once within 50 years, in the Jubile, all Sales were reſcinded and lands reverted to the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former owners. The moſt conſiderable though withall moſt obvious obſervation concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Jewiſh <hi>Agrarian</hi> remains, which is that having extirpated the inhabitants of the Land, they might <hi>Tailler en plein drap,</hi> and ſo avoid the almoſt inſuperable Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties which will cleave to a project that muſt be introduced by alteration of poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>This was the condition of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:116051:46"/> Jewiſh <hi>Agrarian,</hi> which will, if I miſtake not, prove very little conformable to the Notion Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath of it; He thinks not upon the promiſe of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but conſiders the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Lands as a politick conſtitution upon which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was founded, though in the whole Hiſtory of the Bible there be not the leaſt Footſtep of ſuch a Deſign: But in the name of Wonder how can this <hi>Agrarian</hi> be the foundation of that Government which had ſubſiſted more then 45 year without it? The Conſtitution of the Jewiſh Government by Mr. <hi>Harringtons</hi> compute <hi>(Pa.</hi> 16) bears date before the ſending the dozen ſpies to diſcover the Land, but from that Action to the Diviſion of the Land was 45 years, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 14. 10. Again, If this <hi>Agrarian</hi> was meant as Fundamental to the Government, the proviſion was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:116051:47"/> weak and not proper for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the End propoſed, there being nothing in the nature of the <hi>Agrarian</hi> to hinder but that the whole Countrey might for the ſpace of neer 50 years, that is the time between two Jubiles, have come into the hands of one Man, which had been enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Ballance and turn the <hi>Agrarian</hi> it ſelf, as well as all other points of the Government, out of Doors.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Agrarian</hi> of <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> it may be comprehended by what hath been already ſaid of that Commonwealth, that the Deſign of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> in it was not ſo much to attain an equality in the Frame of the Government, as to drive into Exile Riches, and the Effects of them Luxury and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery: This will further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by his endeavour to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this Law not only into Reall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:116051:47"/> but Perſonal Eſtate, though after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he laid it down upon expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that it proved of too hard Digeſtion, and inſtead of it ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the Law forbidding all but Iron-money by which in a way more ſecret and artificial he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the fame End: The ſame is manifeſt alſo by the Proportion of Lands which he aſſigned to every particular Man, which might have been far greater with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out endangering the Equality of the Commonwealth, The ſucceſs alſo is clearly of the ſame ſide; for no ſooner had <hi>Lyſander</hi> by filling the City with Gold and Silver broke the Vow, as I may call it, of Voluntary poverty, but the Commonwealth fell in Virtue and Reputation though ſhe continued a long time after firm in her <hi>Agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.</hi> It is to me as ſtrange as any thing in Hiſtory that <hi>Lycurgus</hi> ſhould find credit enough to ſettle
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:116051:48"/> a Government which carried along with it ſo much want and hardſhip for particular Men, that the totall Abſence of Government could ſcarce have put them into a worſe Condition; The Laws that he made prohibiting the uſe of thoſe things, to enjoy which with ſecurity, is that onely which to other Men makes the yoak of Laws, ſupportable: But it may well be thought, this would have been impoſſible to <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> had he not wiſely obtained Reſponce from <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lphos,</hi> magnifying his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and the Government he went about to introduce after which all Reſiſtance would have been downright Impiety and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Gods. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall have the Fortune to be the Founder of ſuch a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt encounter a very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> apt to be wrought up into a Beliefe that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:116051:48"/> their Legiſlator holds a more then ordinary Correſpondence with Heaven.</p>
            <p>But all this will ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> very little, who (though to bring his <hi>Agrarian</hi> into Credit he had before made a great flouriſh with that of <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon)</hi> does let us know <hi>(Page</hi> 106.) that there is much Diſſimilitude between the <hi>Agrarians</hi> of <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Oceana;</hi> Indeed he is thus far in the right, that the Voice of the firſt was, Every man ſhall be thus Poor; but that of the latter is, No man ſhall be more then thus Rich. I will then leave the Aſhes of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> at peace, and examine a little the Moddel of the <hi>Agrarian</hi> which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Diſcovery I make of it, is that it is Unjuſt. If it be truly aſſerted that Government is founded on Propriety <hi>(Page</hi> 4.)
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:116051:49"/> then Propriety ſubſiſts in Nature before Government, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be fitted to Propriety, not Propriety to Government. How great a ſin then would it be againſt the firſt and pureſt Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of juſtice to bring in a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment not only differing from but directly deſtructive of the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled propriety of <hi>Oceana,</hi> in which there are confeſt <hi>(Page</hi> 101.) to be 300 perſons whoſe Eſtates exceed the Standard of 2000<hi>l. per annum.</hi> Let me not be choakt with the Example of <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> till Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath ſhown Us the power of his perſwaſion with the Nobility of <hi>Oceana,</hi> as <hi>Lycurgus</hi> with them of <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> to throw up their Lands to be parcelled by his <hi>Agrarian, (Pag.</hi> 113.) And when that is done, I ſhall ceaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the injuſtice of it. Not need any one of theſe 300 be put to own a ſhame for preferring his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:116051:49"/> own Intereſt before that of a whole Nation; for though when Government is once fixt, it may be fit to ſubmit Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate to Publique utility, when the Queſtion is of chooſing a Government, every particular Man is left to his own Native Right, which cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed againſt by the Intereſt of all the reſt of Mankind. But in this Caſe the Intereſt of three hundred is not ballanced with that of a whole Nation, but that of ſome few extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ſpirits, who by making Dams in the Current of other mens Eſtates, hope to derive ſome Water to their own parcht Fortunes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond Place the Nature of this <hi>Agrarian</hi> is ſuch that it can never be Fixt, but as 2000 <hi>l.</hi> is held now to be a due Standard of Eſtates, ſo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:116051:50"/> hereafter they may be brought down to 1000 <hi>l.</hi> or a far leſſe Sum; For the whole Body of the People being intruſted with giving a Vote and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Sword, may eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the way of Counſel or Arms agree to make this Change, in which they need not value the Oppoſition of ſuch as enjoy 2000 <hi>l.</hi> whoſe greateſt number can never exceed Five thouſand perſons, <hi>(Page</hi> 100.) a Company too inconſiderable to withſtand Two hundred thouſand Men. <hi>(Page</hi> 200.) It will not be enough to reply that the Law by which the <hi>Agrarian</hi> ſhall be ſettled will hinder this, For it is not to be imagined that thoſe Five thouſand can have a more Legal Title to their 2000 <hi>l.</hi> then the Three hundred now have to the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:116051:50"/> above 2000<hi>l.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>Agrarian</hi> muſt needs be unfixt and flitting, and cannot terminate in any thing but Levelling, or at leaſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the Rate of Eſtates to that paſſe, that the keeping it from going any lower ſhall be the Concern of a greater Number of Men then they make up who have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the further debaſing of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly. As the Jews who have no Land are every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where great Traders; ſo the poſſeſſion of Lands being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by this <hi>Agrarian,</hi> Men who are either Covetous or Ambitious, will imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Eſtates in Forraign Traffique, which being in a manner wholly ingroſt by the Capital City of <hi>Oceana;</hi> that City already too great will
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:116051:51"/> immediately grow into an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Power and Riches ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. The Republique of <hi>Venice</hi> would long ſince have been ſenſible of this inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, but that her Extent being no greater then the Iſles on which the City ſtands; (for Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> hath truly obſerved that to all her other Dominions her Government is provincial) the encreaſe of that one place is the equall Augmentation of the whole Commonwealth. But the caſe ſtands not ſo with our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of <hi>Holland,</hi> where every Province conſiſting of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſeverall Townes, and the Republique of the Union of thoſe Provinces, the Town of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> hath within a few years been ſo aggrandized by Commerce, that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:116051:51"/> of almoſt equall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with all the other Provinces, and hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of late to exerciſe a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in the Diſpoſal of ſome publique Affairs much to the prejudice both of the Liberty and Intereſt of the Reſidue of the Union. An equall if not greater incommodity to <hi>Oceana</hi> would be created by the <hi>Agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> which making <hi>Emporium</hi> a City of Princes, would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Countrey a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Cottagers, able to diſpute precedence with the Beggars Buſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another Conſideration ſuggeſts it ſelf from the great Difficulty in making this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grarian</hi> equall and ſteady; Not only in reference to the various Tenures and Rents of Land in <hi>Oceana,</hi> (which with all other Objections pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:116051:52"/> by Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>(Page</hi> 88.) I on purpoſe omit) but with reſpect to the Flux and Inconſtant value of Money by which this <hi>Agrarian</hi> is computed; We have the experience of all Ancient Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys of Lands and Rates of Commodities how vaſtly they recede from the preſent Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Money, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no natural Value riſes and falls by a thouſand Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; And who knowes but that 2000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> may Two hundred years hence differ as much in Value from this preſent Age, as 2000 <hi>l. per annum</hi> does now from what it did Two hundred years agoe? So the <hi>Agrarian</hi> which is repreſented as the firme immoveable <hi>Baſis</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, muſt like a floa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Bridge undergo all the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:116051:52"/> which Money is ſubject to in its Ebbs and Flows.</p>
            <p>But if there were as many Demonſtrations to Evince an <hi>Agrarian</hi> as there are Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to impugne it, I ſhould notwithſtanding deſpaire of the iſſue, becauſe it muſt make War againſt an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall and Immemoriall cuſtome; The power of Cuſtome is without doubt more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then that of Reaſon, and there is nothing of ſuch Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty as to perſwade Men, at once and crudely, that they and their Forefathers have lived in an Error.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 22.</hi> As the <hi>Agrarian</hi> anſwereth unto the Foundation, ſo doth Rotation unto the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures.</p>
               <p>Equall Rotation is equall viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude in Government, or ſucceſſion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:116051:53"/> unto Magiſtracy conferred for Convenient Terms, enjoying equal vacations as take in the whole body by Parts, ſucceeding others through the free Election or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of the People.</p>
               <p>The contrary whereunto is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longation of Magiſtracy, which traſhing the wheel of Rotation, deſtroyes the life or Natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Commonwealth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>That Ancient Republiques have through a malicious jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie made it unlawful even for perſons of the cleareſt Merit to continue long in Command, but have by a perpetual viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude ſubſtituted new Men in the Government, is manifeſt enough; but with what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe will beſt appear by <hi>Vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Varro, Mancinus,</hi> and the reſidue of weak and paſſionate Commanders which have by this means come to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:116051:53"/> by the <hi>Romans:</hi> And no leſſe by the rabble of Generals often made uſe of by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> while Men of Valour and Conduct have lain by the Walls. It is an Argument of much imperfection in a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment not to dare to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the whole Virtue of her Citizens. And thoſe Orders muſt needs be againſt Nature which excluding perſons of the beſt Qualifications, give Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to others who have nothing to commend them but their Art in Canvaſing for the ſuffrages of the people. Yet this Law hath been as often broke as a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth hath been brought into any Exigency; for the hazard of truſting Affairs in weak hands then appearing, no ſcruple hath been made to trample upon this Order for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:116051:54"/> giving the power to ſome able Man at that time render'd uncapable by the Vacation this Law requires. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the Conſulſhip to <hi>Marius</hi> is ſufficient to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for proofe of this, though if occaſion were it might be backed by plenty of Examples. The <hi>Dilemma</hi> into which a Commonwealth is in this caſe brought is very dangerous; For either ſhe muſt receive a Mortal wound from without, or ſhe muſt give her ſelfe one by gaining the Habit of infringing ſuch Orders as are neceſſary for her Preſervation. I know not what Advantage Mr. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> may foreſee from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this Rotation, <hi>(Page</hi> 213.) for my part I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover no other Effect of it but this, That in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:116051:54"/> like that of <hi>Oceana</hi> taking in the many (For in <hi>Venice</hi> Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> Page 24. confeſſes it to be otherwiſe) where every Man will preſſe forward toward Magiſtracy, This Law by taking off at the end of one year ſome Officers, and All at the end of three, will keep the Republique in a perpetual Minority, no Man having time allowed him to gain that experience which may ſerve to lead the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her True Intereſt either at home or abroad.</p>
            <p>Were the <hi>Agrarian</hi> he aims at once eſtabliſht, the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity would be ſo throughly plumed, that they would be juſt as ſtrong of wing as Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foule are in moulting time. And therefore where Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> goes about <hi>(Page</hi> 25.)
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:116051:55"/> to perſwade the people they need not feare the Nobility, I am of Opinion he might have ſpared his Pains as I ſhall mine in any further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the firſt part of his Preliminaries, ſeeing what remains of any Conſequence will properly belong to thoſe Men to whom I have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Diſquiſition of the Jewiſh Commonwealth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116051:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
